LUCAS MATÍAS BARRERA

Personal Information

LOCATION: Turín, Italy

E-MAIL: lucasmatiasbarrera@gmail.com

LINKEDIN: https://www.linkedin.com/in/lucas-matias-barrera/

ABOUT

I am an Electronics Engineer with over 14 years of experience in the industry, including almost 10 years in the aerospace sector. I'm a very analytical professional, capable of analyzing highly complex scenarios with great attention to detail and a strong market orientation, an aptitude I learned during my last 5 years of work experience.

Over the past four years, I have taken courses in leadership and communication to improve my soft skills, which has allowed me to communicate and lead more effectively and assertively.

I am a very curious person, which is why I began studying philosophy. I am passionate about contemplating the most complex and profound problems that humanity has faced and continues to face. I also thoroughly enjoy arta and I'm currently working on my first sculpture that combines geometry, computer science, and plastic art.

WORK EXPERIENCE

2024-PRESENT

FREELANCE

System Engineering Consultant

System Engineering for aerospace project. Main activities include documentation generation and testing design.

Main goal: Developed a custom programming language to document and analyze automation routines.

2020-2024

VENG

Satellite information based Products Development Manager

Project management and AI development team (4 people) technical leading. Main activities include leading meetings with partners and customers, and products roadmap and commercial strategies definition.

Main goal: Established a 4 people team from the ground up by defining team goals, conducting personnel searches and selecting key roles.

2018-2020

VENG

Business Development

SAR Imagery industry research, business models and commercial strategies definition, and satellite information based products development roadmap definition.

Main goal: Together with two coworkers, started a new business unit up within the company.

2016-2018

VENG

Senior Software Developer

Software development for Tronador Launch Vehicle project.

Main goal: Developed an entire software system for managing mechanical, thermal and electrical interfaces. The software includes features such as data version control and tracking, reports generation (Electrical Harness Manufacturing Sheet, Functional Interfaces and Mass Budget Reports), electrical connections verification, and user profile management among others.

2015-2018 | VENG

Assistant System Engineer for Tronador Launch Vehicle

Support in software development and system modeling for project Systems Engineering team.

Main goal: Deployed a project model for MBSE, and developed an information flow diagram for the company's software tools, aimed to create an Enterprise Ecosystem for SE.

2014-2017 | VENG

Avionics engineer and IVVQ for VEx5A test Launch Vehicle

Responsible for VEx5A telemetry subsystem, support for EI&T operations, and hardware and software development for avionics and EI&T.

Main goal: Developed an Electrical GSE (SW&HW) for test and verification of VEx5A's electrical interfaces.

2011-2014 VITKE

Software Developer

Software development and system design.

Main goal: Designed an end-to-end software system to track the position of city buses and to manage tickets selling.

2013-2014 | FREELANCE

Embedded Hardware and Software Developer

Embedded system definition, design and manufacturing.

Main goal: Developed an entire RFID door lock software and hardware.

2009-2011 | GRUPO SENSOR

Software Developer

Embedded software developer and system designer applied to precision agriculture HW&SW products.

Main goal: Developed a Sprayer Automatic Boom Section Control software, becoming this one of the most sold products of the company.

EDUCATION

2023-2024	Artificial Intelligence Specialization
	Universidad de Buenos Aires, Buenos Aires
2021-2022	Neuro-Linguistic Programming (NLP) Practitioner Diplomate
	PNL Buenos Aires, Buenos Aires
2022-2022	Business Development Diplomate
	CAME Business School, Buenos Aires
2020-2024	B.A. Philosophy
	Universidad Nacional de 3 de Febrero, Buenos Aires
2020-2020	Computational Social Science Specialization
	UC DAVIS, REMOTE
2005-2011	B.Sc. Electronic Engineer
	Universidad Nacional de Rosario, Rosario
2005-2011	A.S. Computer Systems Analysis
	Escuela Superior de Comercio N° 49, Rosario
2001-2005	A.S. Electromechanical Instrumentation and Maintenance
	E.E.T. N°482, Totoras
	2021-2022 2022-2022 2020-2024 2020-2020 2005-2011 2005-2011

PERSONAL PROJECTS

2023 **ELECTRICAL HARNESS CONNECTIONS CHECKER**

Embedded Electronics Engineer

Electronic measurement device with 37x8 analog channels plus a milliohmmeter, with SCPI commands interface that can be used, among other applications, to validate and qualify electrical harness. I designed two different PCB boards (one for analog multiplexing and the other for resistance measurement and system control), developed the device's firmware and software, and designed and 3D printed the device's cabinet using a rackable board concept.

Tools and technologies: KiCAD EDA, Fusion360 CAD, Arduino IDE (C++), Visual Studio Code (Python)

MECHANICAL TOPOLOGY OPTIMIZATION 2023

Software developer

Python software to perform topological optimization of a mechanical piece. I used Code Aster (a FEM solver) to calculate loads and deformations of the piece, and Salome-Meca to modify the piece topology considering the simulation results.

Tools and technologies: Code Aster FEM, Salome-Meca, Python

Courses

2	.023	Project management using Agile (Google, Coursera)
2	022	Level B2 English Courses (British Council)
2	022	Spanish Oratory (Galimi&Alcón, Buenos Aires)
2	020	Systems Engineering (Comisión Nacional de Actividades Espaciales, Buenos Aires)
2	020	Communication, negotiation and leadership (AC Coaching, Buenos Aires)
2	019	Electronics Systems Reliability (Comisión Nacional de Actividades Espaciales, Buenos Aires)
2	019	Space Systems Engineering (Comisión Nacional de Actividades Espaciales, Buenos Aires)
2	019	Model-Based Systems Engineering (The State University of New York, Coursera)
2	019	Artificial Intelligence (Digital House, Buenos Aires)
2	019	Complex Systems Theory: An Introduction (Systems Academy, Udemy)
2	019	Neural Networks and Deep Learning (DeepLearning.Al, Coursera)
2	019	Thinking Complexity (Toulouse Business School, iversity)
2	018	Project Management (Universidad Tecnológica Nacional, Buenos Aires)
2	018	Introduction to Finite Element Method (Universidad de Buenos Aires, Buenos Aires)
2	017	Space Systems (Universidad de Buenos Aires, Buenos Aires)

32-bits ARM based Embedded Systems modeling (UNLP, La Plata) 2016

- Digital Image Processing (Universidad Tecnológica Nacional, Buenos Aires) 2014
- Robotics (Universidad Tecnológica Nacional, Buenos Aires)
- 2014
- 2013 Android Apps Development (Universidad Tecnológica Nacional, Buenos Aires)
- 2010 Network Security (Universidad Nacional de Rosario & CISCO, Rosario)
- 2010 Real Time OS for microcontrollers (Universidad Nacional de Rosario, Rosario)

TEACHING

2018-2019	Universidad Nacional de 3 de Febrero
	Electricity and magnetism course for Sound Engineering career
	Associate Professor
2014-2016	Universidad Tecnológica Nacional
	Robotics course for Electronic Engineering career
	Ad honorem Associate Professor

AWARDS

- 2023 Project selected for the Universidad Nacional del Litoral's Incubation Program
- 2019 Scholarship: Artificial Intelligence to power the country, Fundación Telefónica
- 2017 Best Projects Selection, Argentinean National Innovation Contest (INNOVAR)
- 2013 Best Projects Selection, Argentinean National Innovation Contest (INNOVAR)
- 2000 Best Friend, Rotary Club Argentina

LANGUAGES

SPANISH: Native ENGLISH: Proficient ITALIAN: Beginner

SOFTWARE AND TOOLS

Advanced: Python, .NET (C#, VB), C, MySQL, FreeCAD/Fusion360, KiCAD/Altium Designer,

MS Office Tools (Visio, Excel, Word), LTSpice

Middle: MATLAB, Simulink, LTFX, Enterprise Architect

INTERESTS AND EXTRACURRICULAR ACTIVITIES

3D Manufacturing, Sculpting, Literature, Ethics applied to Al, Music, Complex Systems, Digital Art

REFERENCES

Adrián Unger: Senior Systems Engineer, Satellite Based Solutions Office at VENG

+54 9 11 2517-6412, aunger@veng.com.ar

Natalia Varela: Manager of Satellite Information Based Solutions Office at VENG

+54 9 11 4031-9801, nvarela@veng.com.ar